Test good evening everyone. I will now call to order this November 3rd meeting of Lancaster City Council committees
We will begin with the roll call of members. Mr. Harris if you would
Yes, madam president. Mr. Med here. Mr. Arroyo here. Mr. Cleese. Yeah, miss Craig here
Miss Diaz here. Mr. Hirsch. Yeah the president Baker here Thank you a few reminders for everybody at the top of the meeting I ask that you please silence your phones and devices if you haven't done so already and a reminder that this meeting and its Participants are being recorded tonight. We have meetings of committees of counsel So there are no general public comment periods during this meeting
However committee chairs will call for comments from the public for legislative items, which means bills and resolutions Comments are limited to three minutes per speaker and please begin with your name and your block of residence for our meeting record
finally I'll just make a note this evening that we received requests from South and concern neighbors organization before this meeting began to remove administration resolution 77 2025 from the agenda so that will not be taken up by the Finance Committee counselors we will move to the approval of the October 6 2025 meeting committee meeting minutes motion to approve second we have a
motion and a second counselors any comments on the minutes hearing none Mr. Harris, please. Mr. Mudd. Aye. Mr. Arroyo. Aye. Mr. Cleese. Aye. Ms. Gregg. Aye. Ms. Diaz. Aye. Mr. Hirsch. Aye. President Peke. Aye. That will take us to the personnel committee councillor Kleekst. Thank you madam president
the personal committee has two items on the agenda for tonight and
Both items are nominations for the appointment and we have two nominations for the appointment to the downtown on investment of district authority.
And the nominees are Reverend David Peck and James Wagner, whose terms have expired. And they're willing to be reappointed to continue to serve the community. And there isn't much to say regarding those reappointments, so I'll open up for questions and comments from members of the committee and from council. Please, go ahead.
council please thank you very much I just wanted to just as a matter of
course remind folks that reappointments don't aren't necessarily asked to come to these meetings just new appointments but we appreciate Reverend Peck and mr.
Wagner for their service on this authority I have worked with Reverend Peck specifically in the past and appreciate his serving on this as a reverend in our downtown investment district and his rep and his representation is important on that board and also just thanking both of them for their volunteer service Thank You madam president any other comments or questions from console from the public hearing none I'll make a motion to move these two nominations to November to other to our next console meeting on November 11th second all in favors aye thank you that concludes the
personal committee madam president Thank You councillor clicks will now move to the Finance Committee councillor Arroyo Thank You councillor president I opened up the Finance Committee with the first item on our agenda which is a third
quarter financial report I invite director Tina Campbell to give us the
presentation good evening thanks for providing space to share this report again this is now the third quarterly budget report that we are presenting based on our home
rule charter these slides are not comprehensive so just as a reminder i'll encourage everyone on
council to please refer back to the reports that you would have received on october 21st and again today in in preparation for this meeting those reports end september 30th and are the reports which i will reference this evening i did this in the midterm or in the mid-year budget too but i'm
reporting tonight on financial statements which end september 30th that means that we are three quarters of the way through the year and just as a reminder we need a few days to close a month once it's done so these quarterly reports actually come at the finance committee meeting on the
second regular finance committee meeting of the quarter so it's just slightly over a month after
the quarter closes so we're 75 of the way through the year obviously revenue and expenses are not completely even from month to month but generally you can use 75 as a gauge for any line item in
these reports so ideally we're at 75 or more of revenue and 75 or less of expense as a reminder here's the full budget for 2025 for all of our funds combined our combined expenses equal slightly over 157 million for the year for all five of our funds as of september 30th we're running at about 73.4 percent of budgeted revenue over all the funds and about 57.2 percent of budgeted expenses so we're generally in line with where we should be at this time of year revenue is slightly lower but budgeted expenses are lower i will highlight the expenses a bit more in a couple slides but i do want to point out that the 57.2 percent doesn't include our biggest annual payments
which are our debt payments those were just paid this past friday on october 31st
if we factor those payments in we're at about 67.2 percent of our projected budget so about 10 more and it's still under budget for expenses but it's much more realistic with our total spending
So this is the breakdown of revenue for the general fund. You've seen this a few times starting in the budget process last fall. Our general fund budget for revenue is around $79 million for 2025.
And since the general fund is our largest fund, almost half of the total of combined funds, I want to show the revenue breakdown again, and I'll show the expense breakdown in a minute as well. For the general fund, some highlights from the financial statements. are as follows up here. We're currently at about 80.5% of budgeted revenue for the general fund as of September 30th. I mentioned in the last quarterly update that real estate taxes were running slightly behind the 2024 year-to-date numbers or percentages. They continue to run slightly behind though they're slowly catching up. It was about 1.6% behind at the end of June and it's about 1.4% behind right now. We're continuing to watch this pretty closely. However, the good news is that we're seeing higher collections of past due taxes this year than we budgeted by about $200,000, so that will help to offset some of that.
Earned income tax continues to come in almost exactly to projections, which is great to see. You may have noted in these financial statements that the line for earned income tax
is only showing slightly over half of what we budgeted. I think it's showing at about 53%. So most of the earned income tax comes in as quarterly payments from employers, and those quarterly payments are received in May for the first quarter of the year, then in August for the second quarter, then November, and then February for the final quarter. So we have not received the third quarter payments for those earned income taxes yet. and I mentioned in the mid-year report again that a few of our revenue lines are paid in bigger payments either once or twice throughout the year the debt payments are one of those and then one
of the other ones that I noted in the mid-year presentation was the state pension fund this we
received these funds from the state as revenue and we have now received those funds so that totals about 3.8 million which then does help to push up the revenue for this quarter
and as a reminder because of the amount of expenses related to data center
permit we are treating this similar to how we would treat a grant so that we're tracking expenses directly related to the revenue therefore this doesn't show up in the general fund of financials we'll send a report soon showing those expenses and revenue to date and I will try to include that report in the monthly reports moving forward now that that is in in motion as with revenue I'm just including this slide to show the total expenses budgeted for 2025 in the general fund as well as the breakdown by department or general fund expenses are running as of September 30th at about 58% of the annual budget so significantly lower than than budgeted but as I mentioned earlier this doesn't include the debt payments so if we include that where we have spent about 64% of the budget this year which is still lower than budgeted which is great but not quite as significant so one other piece that I did want to mention I mentioned the debt servicing but I also wanted to mention that we pay pension contributions and those are also paid in October so they are also not reflected in the third quarter financials as with debt servicing these are big payments so between debt servicing and these payments these are our two biggest payments of the year and with both of those payments coming out in October we are about at 75% of expenses at the end of October for the year so because these are the biggest expenses for the for the budget we do anticipate that we'll still end the year under budget since all the major expensive expenses have now been paid out and then finally I mentioned in my mid-year report that public safety overtime increases in the second half of the year and we're seeing this play out in police particularly as we continue to be understaffed until next year hopefully the overtime line in police may end up actually over budget at the end of the year but the staff lines in police continue to be under budget because of the vacancies so those costs will balance each other out and and just as a reminder it is allowable within our code to move expenses within a bureau or department as long as the total expenses for that department or bureau don't go over the approved budget um so we watch these movements but we also recognize that the budgets are always just projections and sometimes one line may run higher and others run lower
than anticipated and just again as a reminder i generally when i'm looking at this i'm more
concerned about overall trends within a department and less about those individual line items so i'm
thankful to say that i'm only seeing general trends of keeping expenses below budget at this point even if some of those individual lines are a bit higher and finally just a few very quick
notes about the four enterprise funds i'm including debt payments in all of these points just because i wanted to show kind of the true costs even though they aren't included
in the september financials so the stormwater fund with the debt expenses included is running about 72 or 72 percent of expenses um budgeted currently we're expecting this to come in slightly under budget in 2025. this was budgeted at a deficit so that the stormwater fund was actually
budgeted with a deficit um in 2025 so we will see a deficit in the fund but it won't be as significant the water fund is running almost exactly exactly as we projected about 75 percent um of the expenses with the with the debt included wastewater fund is running slightly better than budgeted at about 69 of the budget expenses including debt and we're actually projecting that wastewater will end the year with a with a slight surplus surplus which will be helpful to start to build up a much needed cash reserve for that fund to to look out over the next few years and trash or solid waste and recycling is almost exactly as projected the trash fund doesn't have any debt servicing associated with it and most of the expenses have already been collected most of the revenue has already been collected for the year and most of the expenses have already been spent or are accounted for because that's contracted services so we anticipate ending the
year very close to our budget on that and i will stop there and see if you have any questions Thank you director Campbell. I'll open it up to the Finance Committee for any questions or comments full counsel Councilor met Thank You mr. Vice President Thank You director Campbell I appreciate the presentation and my question was seeing that we're currently at around 64% of the expenses Do we foresee that those trends are going to keep moving forward throughout the end of the year? And what are some of the major expenses that we've seen the savings on year-to-date?
today? Yeah, I don't think we're going to end the year at 64%. I think it'll be a little bit higher than that, but I do think we're going to end under budget. The main savings for this is always the vacancy in staff. And when I talk about vacancy, I did want to kind of clarify,
this is just kind of the natural movement of staff. So we're not holding positions open,
but it's it's positions that somebody may leave and then it takes you know a few weeks or a couple of months to refill that role and that savings is what we're seeing the other piece is some of these it's still vacancies but some of the police positions that we haven't been able to fill that we budgeted for thank you for the clarification and with the data center revenues I know there will be additional information given on that with those revenues would those have to come back to council to be spent or how would the revenues made be distributed I know it's gonna be viewed as a grant but yeah we're viewing it similar to a grant so basically that's how we're accounting for it we will spend expenses related directly to the permitting so that won't come back to council but anything additional so any spending additional beyond what the expenses would be specifically for the data center
permitting would come to council thank you and that concludes my questions Thank You councillor med any additional questions or comments from council any from the public that concludes the quarterly financial report but we'll move right into the tax earned income tax exemption report and this report was
requested by council council may remember that a few months ago director Campbell had presented this report to council on what would it look like for a
earned income tax exemption exemption for low-income residents in our city and we are requesting a follow-up to that presentation which will include a summary and hopefully an opportunity to answer any questions uh specifically since we're in the middle of
our budget hearings currently so thank you director campbell for uh bringing this up again
yeah um so i um as councilor arroyo said um we are revisiting this um exemption report we shared
much of this in July, so this will be a review and a repeat of some things, but trying to summarize
it here again as we're in the budget process. So as I did in July, I'd like to add just a small caveat to this report before I jump in. We did do quite a bit of research on this. However, we
have not taken a thorough dive into any of the options that will be presented at the end of the report so those will need to be need to be researched more based on what council is looking
for and additionally I did want to say that we're working with estimates for this process simply
because we still haven't seen a full year of the new earned income tax rate so we're working with projections and assumptions based on what the 2024 numbers were and what we can project for 2025
and so again just depending on how council decides to pursue this for next year we'll move into
further considerations for the options based on the information that we will research and have available then all right so just a quick review earned income tax or EIT as you will see it here and it listed is the tax paid on income earned by anyone who lives in the city so the current rate paid by city residents is 1.1 percent of their income generally the state maximum percentage is 0.6 percent of income but a home rule charter allows municipalities to increase this tax higher than than that max than that state max and the 1.1 percent was voted on in the budget for 2025
with the update for the home rule charter this is the city's portion of earned income tax
the school district also collects earned income tax and they currently collect at a rate of 0.5 percent so the total earned income tax that city residents pay is one point six percent
and just to know earned income tax is only paid on income earned so it's not paid on social security
income which means that many retired individuals if they are living just on social security income
would not be paid would not be paying the earned income tax um and and earn in so what is an earned income tax exemption um this exemption can be determined for income earners making less than a certain amount so the state sets the maximum income tax earned for the exemption at twelve
thousand dollars um we believe that the ceiling that this is the ceiling regardless of home rule status for any municipality in pennsylvania we currently do not have an exemption for earned
income tax there is another tax which is called the local service tax or lst and this is collected
from anybody who works in the city regardless of where they live and we do offer an exemption for this tax if the income is under twelve thousand dollars um our city solicitor reviewed the exemption level requirements and um he did confer with some outside consultants as well and they believe that we cannot go above a twelve thousand dollar income level exemption in the state regardless of the home rule status as i as i stated just a few minutes ago so i'm focusing the data tonight as i did in july on what that would look like for lancaster with a twelve thousand dollar exemption um and additionally we did a meet with the lancaster county tax collection bureau who's graciously provided quite a bit of data for us as we looked into this in discussions in discussions with the tax collection bureau we've determined that really the only feasible option to have these exemptions processed would be to have the tax collection bureau do them because this requires confidential taxpayer information in order to process it it would be very difficult to get that information needed to city staff or other entities to issue these refunds they the tax collection bureau would be willing to do this they've agreed that they could do the work for a fee so that is a helpful process a helpful step in the process additionally the lancaster tax collection bureau received information from a tax collection agency who works with a large portion of the municipalities or who are currently doing the exemption in
in Pennsylvania. So just to note, there's 36 municipalities right now in Pennsylvania of
about 2,000 municipalities total who are doing the exemption. So here's some considerations from both that tax agency that works with the majority of those 36 as well as the Lancaster County Tax Collection Bureau. One of them is that we would want to ensure that there's some provision that people who would receive this exemption would only be eligible if they've lived in the city for the full calendar year otherwise someone with a higher income may move into the city you know late in the in the year but still receive the exemption because of this income threshold the except the exemption must work on a refund basis this is required for two reasons um one we are not able to determine who is making less than the threshold and still
until after taxes are filed so the residents will need to pay the tax throughout the year and then be refunded after they file taxes for that year the second reason is actually a bit more important
because the school district receives a portion of the tax and that portion would not be exempt they would still need to pay that portion the taxes collected as a full percentage and then divided between the city and the school district so it can't be withheld throughout the year residents would need to file taxes by the tax deadline in order for the tax collection bureau to have capacity to process these refunds and that's just something that we talked about with them as we were talking about them processing processing the refunds um the lancaster county county tax collection bureau estimates that only about 50 percent of residents actually file taxes
uh timely so that is another thing to consider um this said however if if there is an exemption option we could see more taxpayers filing in a timely manner than have in the past all right
so i'm going to get into the numbers and hopefully this won't be too many numbers um throwing at you here but these numbers again are estimations using 2024 actual numbers and 2025 assumptions um again we had to make some educated assumptions we don't have historic trends showing us this type
of kind of exemption shift so based on these assumptions the city would receive approximately 130 130 000 from about 3 600 taxpayers making 12 000 or less annually that's if if nothing else happens that's about the amount that we would make um in 2025. currently the tax collection bureau estimates that only about half of the taxpayers earn taxpayers earning below the
12 000 threshold file taxes as i um as i mentioned and we're estimating that approximately 20 percent more taxpayers will file with the incentive of a refund um so this will actually equal approximately 258 000 in earned income tax collection collected with a total of about 4600 individual taxpayers the dollar amount almost doubles with this additional 20 percent because more taxpayers earn closer to the 12 000 mark than the lower amounts so we anticipate that the filings would be on that end which actually means those those higher amounts therefore for the purposes of an estimate we're using 258 000 as the estimated lost revenue to the city since technically this would no longer be available as tax revenue so of this 258 000 we now need to consider non-resident earned income tax and this gets a little complicated so hopefully i can walk through this well enough the non-resident earned income tax applies to people living in
the city but working in a different municipality residents are charged one earned income tax so residents are charged just just one earned income tax this will first go to the municipality in which they live if the municipality that the resident lives in decides to not charge earned
income tax or if that income tax happens to be lower than the earned income tax where they work or if the resident is refunded the earned income tax the outside municipality where the resident
works now has the right to collect their non-resident tax so for example if somebody lives in the city but works in manheim township manheim township will generally not collect a non-resident tax because the city gets the tax first before the outside municipality
however if the resident living in lancaster city gets an exemption of the 1.1 percent rate in essence this means that the resident has not yet paid an earned income tax so then manheim township would be eligible to receive a non-resident tax at their rate which is 0.6 because they don't have an exemption they would receive that funding and then the resident would
receive a refund of 0.5 percent instead of the full 1.1 percent so based on what the tax collection
bureau could help us calculate based on 2024 actual numbers and 2025 projection projections
it looks like approximately 117 000 of the 258 000 would be paid to other municipalities
the taxpayer would receive about 141 000 of this as a refund so this would be an average refund of about 42 dollars per resident for the 4 700 residents approximately that we're estimating would file and then we would have a fee that the tax collection bureau would charge for the work which would be approximately 47 000 it's about 10 per per filing so our total outlay with the revenue reduction and the expenses for processing would be approximately 304 000 and we estimate that less than half of that or around 141 000 would actually go back to the taxpayers it's a lot of numbers so here's a graphic that can hopefully help to simplify this um so again using the estimates the full amount of revenue loss and expenses would be divided up as this dollar shows with approximately 38 percent going to other municipalities through the non-resident earned income tax approximately 15 percent in processing fees and then approximately 40 percent 46 ultimately going back to the residents so um as i said in july ultimately council will have will need to make a decision about pursuing an exemption it can be done thankfully the tax
collection bureau is willing to do the processing however given that potentially more than half of
the total financial outlay may not actually end up going back to the taxpayers we also wanted to offer some other options so here's a couple of them we could consider allocating the approximate portion that would have been refunded so the full amount the 304 000 into the critical repair program this targets support for low-income individuals and it would mean that all the funds would be kept for use by city residents we could consider allocating the approximate portion to the lancaster water assistance program for utility support for lower income households we could designate that portion to only be used for in-city residents right now the water assistance program is used for the whole county. It's run in conjunction with CAP, and we've been putting in approximately $50,000 in the past few years to support this work. Last year, approximately 98 households were supported through the program, so more funding towards that program could definitely be used. And finally, we could consider new programs. We won't have capacity before 2026 to flesh out how the programs might actually function, But we can budget for the program in 2026 so that it can be defined and implemented in 2026 with the new administration I think I'll stop there Thank You director Campbell
Open it up to the Finance Committee for any questions or comments
Okay. Well before we go to council actually do still have one kind of question because this is based on a reimbursement model
Would this be upon request of the taxpayer? So the taxpayer would actually have to go and request this refund. Correct. Yes. Thank you any questions or comments from full counsel counselor I met Thank You mr. vice president thank you again director Campbell I appreciate us meeting again
on this important issue so my first question is if you could just explain again that the 46% would be if we like they would get 4.6 cent like on the dollar rather than if we did a different program it would be 100% of the funds could be used this is showing it sort of as where the costs would lie so basically yes that's you're exactly right 46 46 cents on the dollar would go back to to the taxpayer ultimately in this scenario or we could just kind of budget the full amount to go back to residents of the city and also to
clarify if they did not file taxes or request the exemption funds they would not be eligible for it and my final question is with the potential process of exploring a new program would council have to and amend the budget as it's currently presented to include that amount to be spent in the next fiscal year as a one-time allocation yes the budget would need to be amended we don't
we haven't done the first reading of it yet so it doesn't need to go through the ordinance to amend it but we would need to amend it and bring it back to council that includes my questions thank you Thank You councillor med any councillor
Hirsch Thank You vice president Thank You director Campbell for the presentation so just to clarify it sounds like you are saying that the two
fifty eight thousand two three hundred four ish thousand has not been included as a line in the proposed 2025 budget. That's correct. OK. A couple of comments I would make. I don't think it makes more I don't think it makes logical sense to spend more than our residents would benefit on a program especially when a lot of those funds are going to municipalities that have a wealthier tax base frankly. So I just don't think it makes sense to do a program in which we're spending more to administer it than the benefit is actually being received by city residents. It brings me no joy to say what I'm going to say here
but I feel it needs to be said and I think this is my comment I'm particularly directing
it to my colleagues on council.
The budget proposal that was given to us on October 12th it not only showed a drawing of a million dollars in reserve in the year 2026 it also in a presentation showed over a 10-year timetable that our reserve would be significantly depleted and I think that if we were to allocate an additional amount of some kind of resident benefit that we need to I mean budget that obviously but I think in general I would encourage the administration to reevaluate the budget that they have proposed because I I personally don't feel great about drawing a million dollars from reserve next year as its budgeted I mean and I to compliment city staff because as you showed in the in your report previous to this city hall generally does a good job of keeping expenses under budget but i guess i'm making this comment now one to encourage council to look for opportunities to cut back on cost to not draw upon reserve and in particular if we are going to implement some
kind of program in which we you know whether it is the water program whether it is critical repair or
if we would go with the exemption i think we need to think long and hard about adding that additional expense in a budget that i frankly feel is a little over expensed and i'm open to dialogue with my colleagues on council and with the administration on that but i felt i had to say that that concludes my comment thank you councillors council president thank you and thank you councillor hirsch for that um this is a little bit of a question but kind of also a comment for council i think that i do agree that i want to make sure that whatever we implement has the best um outcome for our residents and i'm not sure that an exemption uh to get 46 percent of their dollar back to them that's not an exemption that's just um but i am interested in in looking at ways that we can directly impact folks and i think that a water bill assistance program you know not everyone is a homeowner critical repair extremely important i think we still need to prioritize that but when we're looking dollar for dollar at where we could
spend here a water bill assistance program that could that's designated for city residents and I'm assuming could have income restrictions just as it as it stands today and beef up the funds that we're already doing in that program and making it more impactful if we serve 98 families imagine what we could do if we invest the dollars that we would have otherwise though we otherwise get you
know this this you know relatively small amount of the budget that we get from these filings to just reinvest them directly back into the folks that would
be you know potentially struggling with things like water bills so I would just
encourage council to think about that and thank you for confirming the income restriction requirement Thank You council president councillor met Thank You mr. president just one last question just to clarify this would have to be a a one time allocation because we wouldn't be able to build it into future budgets correct. If we did we'd have to do it every year. Yeah it would have to be done every year.
So yeah. Yeah. Thank you. I just want to clarify that for the other members of council. DIRECTOR DEWOLF Thank you councillor Mead. Good question. DIRECTOR DEWOLF Councilor Arsh. DIRECTOR ARSH I do just want to briefly expand upon my comment which is that I would absolutely support
you know a program like this that would support people at a time that I think a lot of people economically
are hurting right now.
I don't want to come across as not supportive of a program like that. But I think right now the budget, again, as budgeted,
is drawing upon $1 million of reserves at a time that I don't think we should be doing that. And so unless we make adjustments elsewhere,
this would just be additional draw on reserves,
assuming no other changes so that that's kind of the purpose of my my comment there thank you counselors yeah i'll just say that uh as a reminder when we you know i won't speak for council but i remember the intention of going through the home rule process was thinking about
the financial sustainability of the city in the future and for our residents so to keep that in mind as we explore some of these programs that will cost a significant amount of money also like the idea around exploring new programs as councilor president as council president mentioned
um some of the programs that we have in existence do benefit property owners but we don't really have anything in existence that benefits low-income renters um so there there is an opportunity there to be discussed around you know in the future what does a program that benefits
low-income renters look like and could this be an opportunity to fund something like that so yeah any additional questions or comments from council all right i'll welcome any questions or
comments from the public you may need to turn that on if you're the first person up and you can raise or lower it as you need it to testing there you go yeah darling bird and street i would ask about the other municipalities 38.4 percent how would they know whether or not city residents paid their
EIT tax I'm sorry miss bird can you speak in the light just so the streaming can pick it up thank you someone to track down who paid or didn't pay if
they were exempt correct yeah all of all of the tax collection is actually done through the Lancaster County Tax Collection Bureau so like any of the municipalities would be collected through them and they're able to see where they work and where they live so that is automatically. So they would be able to tell if they paid the earned income tax or not.
Thank you. Tony Dastra
700 block New Holland Avenue just quick statement at the beginning we shouldn't
ever worry about balancing our budgets
off of the backs of our poorest residents there are other ways to do it but I do have some questions I actually want to thank you because this gave more context to some questions I had from the past so I appreciate that part of my frustration in looking at these figures is that they come from a small place and this isn't you you did exactly what you were tasked to do this is more this side of any conversation when we intentionally look small everything we see is small and I think we as a public still deserve to know why in writing we don't believe we have an exemption above the 12 000 cap we need to see more of the reasoning as to why i haven't seen the reasoning and it should be noted that if we're talking about tax changes in a more robust way sure some municipalities could still take their 0.5 0.6 percent but we know that if these municipalities don't have a home rule charter they're not going to be exceeding what was already set in place so
So without getting too wild with this, I think that we need to make sure it's clear that some residents will definitely receive a full refund. Other residents may still be paying another municipality a tax, but to Ms. Bird's questions,
the municipalities need to know about that tax and get that tax. And as we balance our budgets with different tax rates, sure, we can't offset what tax a municipality might take from a resident. we do offset the increases we would make to their taxes in a local way and the more wealthy individuals in our community paying a share of taxes in would have a impact here and still benefit those residents who are taking the municipality taking 0.5 still so there's a conversation still to be had about these numbers especially when you expand beyond the 12 000 cap potentially if you start looking at other tax caps and which i personally still believe we can do So, yeah, I guess my biggest question for tonight comes from prior meetings. I've heard that we could automate the refund. So if the government was to enact a refund program, could we make it that it's automatic? And if not, why? I don't know the answer to that. I would have to get back to you. I'm not sure. I mean, all I know is that we've talked to the Tax Collection Bureau, and they've talked about an application process. I just want to confirm something about the structure of the exemption. I think this was discussed multiple times last year, and that is that the exemption is kind of a cliff. If I'm making below the threshold, I pay zero, but if I make above the threshold, I'm taxed on that initial 12,000. So I think the tax on 12,000 would be 132, so I would go literally from zero if I made just under to $132 owed if I go just over? Correct. If there's an exemption, that would be correct. Okay. So that arguably is another argument against going the exemption route because, again, two dollars of difference, vastly different impact. Then just a point I would make is I think the Home Rule Commission's interest in the
Exemption was to hold harmless a broad class of lower-income Lancaster County taxpayers
critical repair in the water assistance program, I think targeted fairly small number of households I Honestly, don't know if there could be a program that would benefit a broader range of lower-income households But if there were anything like that feasible, I would encourage council in the administration to consider it. Thank you. Thank you Just to put a finer point on that. I think yeah the the opportunity like the problem with that we're looking to try to solve is how do we lessen the impact on low-income residents so looking for a
more efficient way to to make those dollars count I think will matter so great well barring no additional public comment Thank You director Campbell for
the presence here for the second presentation on this I know it's been a topic that council has been very interested in and we want to just do what's best for for our residents here so thank you so much with that I will
move to the third item on the agenda which is administration bill number 13 2025 which is authorizing a penvest loan for lead water line replacement and director campbell's already here to speak to that i am as soon as i can figure out there we go all right um yeah so i am not going to
talk as much for this one daryl is going to talk a little bit um but we're bringing uh to you tonight
a bill authorizing debt from penvest for lead line replacement work so as you are aware we are under a federal mandate through the lead and copper rule to replace all of our known lead service lines by 2037. this project will replace 108 of those lines as daryl will share shortly the total cost of the
specific project is about 1.7 million we've applied through penfest which is the state
revolving loan fund for this full amount and we were awarded a grant of nine
hundred and fifty three thousand from Penvest with the remaining amount of
seven hundred and fifty six thousand in a loan this is just a small portion of
the web lines that we need to replace so we will continue to apply through Penvest they recommended that we applied for lower amounts to get to have more potential to get the grant funding as we work to complete this project this project was included in the 2026 capital plan which was approved in September and
you would have approved a resolution for the application for these funds when we
applied back in June and Daryl's gonna provide some details good evening Daryl Peck with Concord public finance good to be here before you tonight Tina already gave you the big overview I gave you out a presentation with I'm going to talk quickly over the first few pages of narrative the rest of the schedule is a lot of numbers i just give it to you because i feel like i have to give it to you um as teen indicated you know you're proceeding with the water system improvement project uh to replace lead lines at
about 108 uh residences in the city the total cost of the project is approximately 1.7 million in connection with the project the city received a funding offer or a financing offer from
pennsylvania infrastructure investment authority you probably know it as penvest
um penvest funding offer is obviously very attractive uh it consists of the two components um the $756,132 loan uh with a term of 30 years and an interest rate for the entire term of one percent. You were also awarded the grant of $953,206 grant, meaning no repayment. So you'll
be able to do the $1.7 million project, improve the water system, and your repayment terms are $756,000 and interest thereon. On page two is the timeline. So the city actually received the penvest funding offer back in mid-july obviously we're before you tonight to talk about the financing you know the presentation and referral to council the plan would be have first reading of the ordinance at your next meeting on november the 11th and then have second reading on november the 25th the timing of the project currently projects anticipated the bidding and awarding
The project is anticipated for sometime in December, and the project could begin as early as January of next year.
We'll actually close on the PennVest financing on January 13th, so the funds will be available. Both the grant and the loan will be available to pay for the project.
The project is actually estimated to be completed by the end of 2026. as i said there's a lot of numbers on the on the back here but in quick summary uh the annual debt
service for the $756,000 loan in 2026 interest only will be a little under $6,700 uh 2027 you'll start paying principal midway through the year uh the total payments of principal and interest in 2027 will be just under $22,000, and then beginning of 2028 through and including 2057, you'll pay the $29,185 on an annual basis for the remaining term. All the detailed numbers are behind this. I don't really look at those, but it's here for you if you want to see it. I often show you a graph of before and after. Obviously, looking at these numbers, it would
to be imperceptible obviously a great project for the city and we're prepared to move this forward for you and and just to note this is the water fund um so this is the the enterprise fund any other questions just one quick one and maybe you're going to get to that uh is there a prepayment
penalty for this for the loan portion no there's not okay thank you you took one of my questions i forgot i was running this uh that's okay you took one of my questions so that's good to know
I'm just kind of curious. How did they arrive at the balance like the between the grant amount and the loan amount?
It's a it's a nice balance, but I'm just curious Unfortunately, we don't get that information. So we don't know how they interesting do the calculation but we do know I will say one of the reasons that they recommended that we do these in smaller chunks is because they look at the neighborhood and the Average median income for of that neighborhood and so that's some of how they determine the grant So I'm not sure how they actually get to the exact amount
Got it based on like the actual replacement cost per household interesting. Okay. Thank you Councilor met Thank You council royal. My only question is the projected debt
Impact that's already in the projections for the next couple years Because I this was originally part of the capital plan. So
The debt service will be will have no budgetary impact to the current projections, right?
Thank you. Thank You councillor mid Councillors, I think thank you vice president And I think councillor Arroyo was kind of thinking sort of along the lines. I was thinking just curious mainly for
other pen best financings do they encourage the 30-year repayment schedule or is that something we have optionality and is this just like the best timetable for this particular loan I'm curious about that yeah I mean they offer the terms with 1% interest sometimes it's worth looking at those a little
further out but also with no prepayment penalty that's helpful as well to do the debt servicing
in the budget thank you Thank You councillor Hirsch any additional questions or comments from council any questions or comments from the public
would what copies of this be made available to the public or do we have physical copies by chance I mean I don't have enough for everybody and this will be made available to the public thank you great any additional further for the
presentation great well with that I will motion to move administration bill
number 13 to the next full council meeting all those in favor aye that concludes the Finance Committee council president thank you very much
all right as we disconnect and reconnect tech we will now move to the Community Planning Committee and councillor Craig Thank You council president well we have
an extent of extensive agenda here this evening the first item on the agenda
being a review of the Historical Commission's recommendation for 623 East
Mifflin Street is there anybody here for the project good evening
what I plan on doing is at 623 there's some existing garages and I plan on just breaking those down and building five single-family homes on a lot that's
that's what the plan is sounds pretty straightforward to me great for are there any questions from the committee questions or comment from council as a whole second maybe sorry I was thinking out so Craig I was just confirming that these were recommended for approval by the Historical Commission and just curious mr. Henry D your background in development construction of you facilities management and I also own 451 East Mifflin Street which was I renovated the whole thing it's a laundromat right now so that's my background I have some background construction great thank you thank you I think that'll be all okay
thanks so much and I'll make a motion that we move this recommendation to full council on the 11th second all those in favor aye thank you second item on the
agenda is the historical historical Commission's recommendation for 248 South Ann Street is there anybody here for that good evening Jeffrey Zorman from Ann Street and the owner I recently purchased a house and on the properties
there is a garage that is very badly rotted has much structural damage I
would like to tear that down put in a small pre-manufactured shed fence in the property so that it can be used as a play area for my children thank you so
much I believe this was all also recommended by the Historical Commission for approval are there any questions from the committee any questions from full council thank you I'll make a motion to move this project to a full council on the 11th thank you and all those in favor aye thank you so
much and now we're gonna do we have several local shares accounts I think what I want to do first is have director Campbell give us a brief overall about what a local shares is we'll do that first okay that's fine thank you so much
I am NOT director Campbell but I am that is okay the grant manager so a quick
overview and key points on the local shares account grant program this is a statewide LSA program which reinvests gaming revenue into projects that
improve quality of life across Pennsylvania communities so uses for funding can support public infrastructure community facilities
equipment vehicles I'm sorry equipment and vehicles demolition and planning design work grants can range anywhere from twenty five thousand ten million dollars with no local match required the benefits to the community bring it so So LSA brings outside investments
into projects that might not otherwise be funded. So these improve neighborhoods, facilities, and services. The LSA program also creates opportunities for partnerships within the city and other organizations. So while the city applies as the primary applicant,
the nonprofits and other organizations are the direct beneficiaries of these funding sources. So where other organizations cannot apply directly, apply on their behalf and then develop stronger partnerships through the work that we do with the organizations so as of now the track record since 2022 when the program opened we've applied for 30 different projects to be funded 11 of those have been awarded and a little over 5.9 million has been awarded to Lancaster City to support different various types of programs and and projects so with the 2024 applications we're still waiting for
those dollars to be distributed to different programs and projects in the city and then in 2025 we're planning on applying for ten new projects so we'll
be hearing from some of those today thank you although you know I know this
sounds a little bit repetitive that I asked for this information each time but I think it's relevant to everyone so that everybody knows what local shares
is all about okay that being said we are going to move into the first applicant
for local shares administration resolution number 69 an application to
local shares accounts program by Union Community Care I would ask that each applicant come and give us a brief because there are a few of them give us
a brief overview of what your project is going to be and Oh mr. Reichenbach good to see you push your button I guess I forgot how to do that good evening councilman mayor and everybody in attendance I'll be very brief because I
know your time is valuable thank you for the consideration my name is Jimmy reichenbach i'm the chief impact officer from union community care for those who aren't familiar
we're a federally qualified health center that operates in lancaster lebanon and chester county so we currently see about 65 000 patients a year we are known for the fact that we won't turn
anybody away regardless their ability to pay uninsured under insured or likewise we're going to see you for care so we have medical dental behavioral health social services urgent cares in-house pharmacies and on and on it continues to grow specifically for the local shares account we are looking to do a renovation of our south duke street property for those of you who aren't familiar i'm a few the boys and girls club on south duke street we are right behind that at
625 south duke that location currently houses a full primary medical dental and a in-house
pharmacy location on the dental location on the second floor has been renovated within the last five years. The pharmacy was just built out last year, but the medical location is original. So
when you go into the medical, we see over 10,000 patients a year at that location. It's extremely
busy, but it looks like a bit of a 90s location. So we're looking for local shares to help us fund the renovation of that location. We plan to be there for several more generations. We've been there for several decades already, and we'll be requesting a million dollars in LSA money to be
able to fully renovate the first floor to kind of bring the technology and the space needs up to the 21st century happy to answer any questions spectacular are there any questions from committee questions from council as a whole council craig thank you and thank you for being here does this application represent the in total cost of the project or that be a different
a higher number that'll be uh it'll likely be a higher number um we're committing operational resources to this as well because we recognize the importance to the community um so we're looking forward to um you know adding those funds and we'll also be looking for other grant dollars
as well to try to leverage those resources wherever we can but ultimately this is a need because it's a high use facility so we'll be adding additional dollars thank you sure spectacular
are there any further questions from council nope okay i will make a motion to move resolution
administration resolution 69 2025 to full council on the 11th second all those in favor aye aye thank you thank you for your time thank you um the next um one on the list is administration resolution number 70 authorizing an application for local shares account program by univision childcare either or good evening good evening councilmembers my name is
champagne Domingo I am a tenant operating univision childcare but I am applying as a partner of Southwest End Holdings we are the proud new owners of
the historic slave maker lock building so I'm here tonight to share the slave
maker renewal project in an effort to revitalize one of Lancaster's true landmarks it sits on Southwest End Avenue between 1st Street and 2nd Street we are home to about 35 current small businesses including Lancaster Conservancy petals with style posh bridal and luxe salon and spa and the bird in hand farms corporate office at nearly at over 90,000 square feet and nearly three acres most sites of that scale are either industrial or
residential and not thriving mixed-use campuses many of the businesses have
been there for years and some even decades so we're looking for funds to
renovate that property thank you what's the the cost of your application we are seeking a million dollars in local share account support for energy
efficient systems stormwater management and green infrastructure repaving of the parking lot the historic facade restoration and a playground and community space thank you and I'm sure somebody's gonna ask is that's the total cost for the project no ma'am that is just what like the critical needs and what would the total cost for the project be we are still getting estimates
I think the biggest
Again, I'm sorry. I don't know what I don't know. This is like the first project we're doing of this capacity
So I think the biggest thing that we're struggling with now is like the stormwater, which is also a city issue. I see
so we had budgeted for About two hundred twenty five thousand but in speaking with the city It's probably gonna be more than that. So I at this time, I don't know. Thank you. Are there any questions? from the committee Questions from council as a whole
Thank You. Yes, okay It's in the summary that we received but it would be exciting if you could share
What this would mean for univision child care specifically in in this renovation project briefly Yes, so there's also another Space so I just recently opened in in july with the help of the city arpa funds and that center is for 60 students we have almost already kind of outgrown that we have a standalone property on that space that is about 9 000 square feet so being able to now go from 60 students to about 160 students employing 15 to 20 additional staff with adding unit a second location for Univision so right then our current location would become more of a nursery and would be infants and toddlers and then the second location would be preschool and even kindergarten thank you that's exciting thank you any further questions from council thank you ladies I'll make a motion to move resolution number 70 2025 to full council on the 11th second all those in favor aye thank you administration resolution number 71 authorizing applications to local shares account program by the thaddeus stevens foundation good evening ladies pam smith that is stevens college of technology joined by my colleague
jenny german as ms craig had said before we've been uh before this committee previously for lsa funds, but as a quick reminder, our students, eight of our programs come together to participate
in the student home construction project as one of our signature focuses of the college. We're currently working on a project that's on Stevens Avenue. Stevens Avenue is located
in the southeast section of the city between Chesapeake and Schuylkill. Provided a little bit of a graphic for you, just so you can visualize where that is. The fund, the focus of our funds for this lsa application are on the fourth duplex that's there where the blue star is
so that will be a project that we'll do in 2728 which aligns with the funding application for this so we're looking for a million dollars out of this application to help us complete that duplex project the whole project itself will provide eight total units that will be owner occupied and this would be the last one that we're building in that wonderful thank you um are there any questions on the project from committee uh counselor craig no questions just a comment
i got the opportunity to tour one of the uh other properties and you guys did an amazing job so um you know barn uh looking forward to this one being built as are we yeah questions from council as a
whole comments wonderful that was easy i'll make a motion to move um resolution number
71 to full council on the 11th second all those in favor aye thank you so much um we're moving on to administration resolution 72 authorizing application to local shares account program by South and Street concerned neighbors good evening ladies
okay turn your turn your mic on there you go okay I actually have three of my board members with me Jabari Betty and Linda our project is South and Stevens project and it consists of land that was donated to South and concerned neighbor from Thaddeus Stevens Foundation. It was formerly known as the SACN Franklin Street Project and it's located at 615 Stevens Avenue. Thaddeus Stevens Foundation gave us a 10,000 square foot piece of land. SACN will construct two-story buildings with mixed use approximately 3,000 square feet. There will be two three-bedroom affordable apartments on the top floor and two retail spaces on the bottom floor we're looking for a fresh food mark not a bodega that would sell vegetables fruits and milk and then a pizza deli shop to date we finally attained our deed which included zoning approval for the mixed use on september the 2nd 2025 we have schematic drawings almost complete and we're working with ted williams we met with the city staff chief planner lauren finn and the crew on monday october the 31st to discuss the project and directions for moving forward our timeline goals is we're hoping to hire a construction manager by next week we will hire a design team before thanksgiving to keep this project moving forward our funding we estimated to be about it was about 3.5 million dollars that probably went up a little bit We have already been awarded about half of that money. When the state budget passed, we have a line item for RACB for $1 million, and we have our match, and we understand that we will need to have our own consultant for the grant. The city cannot help us with the grant. We have on our project committee Keith Holland, A.J. Jackson, Andrew Marshall, Betty Jones, Carol Godfrey, and Darlene Bird. Thank you. Now, you said the total cost for your project was? About $3.5 million. And you're about halfway there? About halfway. And do you have any projections on when it might be finished? No, not yet. Not until we actually hire our design team. We know not to say that now until we actually have a schedule from our firm.
Okay. Okay. Are there any questions from the committee? Questions from council as a whole? Wonderful. I'll make a motion to move resolution 72 2025 to full council on the 11th.
Second all those in favor. All right. Thank you so much We're moving on to administration resolution number 74
Authorizing an application to local shares account program by chestnut housing Good evening. Good evening. Thanks for having us this evening. Thank you councillor Craig and full council and mayor appreciate your time I
I will also just give a brief summary of our project request and what we're working on
This is essentially duplicating a request that you might recall we made last year since the 2024 LSA Awards have not yet been Finalized by the state we felt it was kind of good due diligence to come back with the same request this year For you all so just a reminder of what we're working on This project is Dinah's Hill Apartments to renovate the former Strawberry Hill restaurant site in the southwest part of the city into 11 affordable apartments and two commercial office spaces for community nonprofits to to lease including our organization It's about a 3.8 million dollar project budget to date about 2.4 million of that has been committed to the project So about two-thirds of the funding has been committed most of that was committed since I was here a year ago ago making a similar request so the good news for us is if a million dollars is awarded which is our request either from 2024 or 2025 we certainly have enough funding to be able to
move forward with the project yeah I think I'll leave it at that for now our our timeline is a little bit fluid based on these funding requests but our hope is if funding comes through in the
quarter from the 2020 24 requests that we can move forward with construction by the middle of next year he answered my question so I don't have any I have any
questions we are super eager to get to work on this one we just need a bit more
money okay questions from the committee questions from council as a whole Thank You councillor Craig you made mention of the funding delay is that directly related to the state budget impasse is that why LSA has been delayed in general
it's a long process but is it is that the reason why we're still waiting on 2024 do you have I see Jenna sort of nodding in the background I mean I can't
say we received a 2023 LSA grant for another project and that award was we
were notified in November of that year so it would be I mean this month would
be a similar timeline for the 2024 awards so yes it is just a very long process yes it is I don't know if you have more up-to-date information I don't so we go off of the CFA timelines and what
we were told for this year was that we could expect it to go anywhere from eight months to I think it's been a year and two months before so they were hopeful that we would get it in it I guess it would have been September of this year but clearly we're still waiting so we're kind of relying on their deadline or their timeline, but it doesn't have, at least not what we're aware of, doesn't have any connection to the state budget.
Sure. Great. Thank you for that. That ambiguity is tough because prices for these projects keep going up and up and up, and you apply a year and a half ago, and now you're back again. I feel your frustration. Okay. All right. I will make
a motion to move this application resolution number 74 to full council on the 11th second all those in favor aye thank you so much yeah thank you all we are now moving to administration
resolution number 78 authorizing the sale of 843 Fremont Street by a realtor
director Delphs good to see you good to see you too council craig you have a lot of items on your committee uh i do i usually do i'm quite used
to that by now okay well uh good evening city council mayor sirachi um i know this item has
come before you uh in the past in some uh other forms just wanted to uh circle back and give a
little additional context about this particular item uh earlier this year city council amended the city code to allow real estate sales through a licensed real estate broker so that that action has already happened this resolution tonight which is 78 2025 before city council this month in november provides the authority to retain the firm compass real estate to manage the process for marketing the property at 843 fremont street that also includes evaluating the offers and ultimately selecting a buyer for that property as well. Some of you may be familiar with Compass Real Estate already. The city has selected Compass because it's a commercial realtor who we have worked with before. They have a deep understanding of city operations and city goals. They've also had a lot of success in working with the city directly and the administration is comfortable and confident that they can deliver an effective process and achieve results on this important property. This resolution, I think it's important to note also that this resolution includes exhibits that clarify the realtor's role, and the exhibits include a brokerage agreement. It also includes a marketing plan that Compass has developed and also an evaluation matrix that will be used for ultimately selecting among any offers that we get for 843 Fremont. Just a few more words about the evaluation process. Compass and the city will utilize that evaluation matrix to rate and rank any offers that we receive.
And you may have noticed that there are stated criteria within that exhibit in the evaluation matrix.
And a couple of those criteria, I'm very happy to report, they emphasize consistency with the comprehensive plan and ultimately the land use and community objectives for the neighborhood. The evaluation matrix ultimately is intended to allow city officials to come to a good decision that balances the price of the property with community benefits as well. I think we've had some questions in the past about whether this process is intended to
Achieve the highest price that we receive. Of course, that's an important consideration given some of the budget Comments made earlier and our concerns about balancing a budget However, it's important to note that price is just one factor and there are other community objectives that we may wish to achieve the council may wish to achieve with this site as well and it provides that flexibility so I think that that's the long and the short of it but I'm happy to answer other questions that you
might have okay thank you so much are there questions from the committee
councillor Craig thank you director Delveson sorry if I missed this but is Is there a deadline on up until we will we will be accepting offers for the property or would this be open ended. Yeah I don't have any dates tonight. It's really intended to be driven by the marketing plan that Compass has put together and then really we're looking for a good set of offers that we can that we can compare amongst those offers. I don't know. Mayor Sirachi do you have any other information on the dates. just that we would like to have more than one offer which is the reason why
we opted to use a realtor to market the property when we did this you know as you recall there's three ways that we can sell a property through public auction through a sealed bidding process and through a realtor and the realtor is
now something new that was changed as director Delph's mentioned so this will get it on the MLS listing and then in addition compass will be reaching out to other prospects and then of course there have been people that have come forward to the city there have been two individuals that have expressed interest
those individuals will also be their contact and information will be shared with compass and it will be an open open opportunity for people to make a decision and I think put in an offer and I think that the matrix really as I just want to underscore what director Delve shared is that you know the money isn't
everything ultimately the the next administration will decide what the outcome will be of that property and and of course alignment with the comp plan will be taken into consideration community benefit cost and then you know obviously tax implications whether or not it's going to be a for-profit or
nonprofit use thank you thank you councillor Craig and thank you for the presentation my only question is moving forward with compass if if organizations
or parties were interested in purchasing the property would they go directly to
compass or would they contact the city first yeah thank you good question my understanding is that any parties are eligible to make an offer to ask questions first and foremost and then if they desire to put in an offer a
proposal they would do that directly with compass thank you thank you I'm looking at the the agreement here and I just want to clarify if I'm understanding this properly so essentially this would allow this contract between the the realtor is the length of 365 days in the event that
there's no sale in that time and we would only pay any brokerage broker fees
if there's a sale within that time and then there's a couple of other very
specific things that might cause us to have to pay the fee but we don't pay until there's a sale essentially yes that's correct that's my understanding as well okay thank you are there any further questions from council go ahead thank you so just to clarify um apologies if i missed this um but i think for the benefit of the public it might be good um could you just clarify who the final decision rests with is it council or is it the administration as far as who you know the property ultimately gets sold to yep thank you councillor hirsch as this is set up now based upon the results of that evaluation matrix it would be
the mayor or the administration that would make that determination and then bring that report
back to council so the final decision would rest with council is what you're i would rest with the
mayor and the administration okay okay and report back to council okay in the way it's stated in the
resolution yes and i think i recall that from when we passed the original resolution so that makes
sense yes thank you are there any further questions from council i'll i'll entertain questions or comments from the public thank you well here's mr dash just coming oh sorry counselor greg uh tony dash is 700 block in new holland avenue i think everybody already knows that i personally disagree with this but i just want to understand what the vision here is if a sale does occur like um i understand we've gone through bidding processes they haven't gone smoothly i'm recognizing that the city is wanting to get rid of the property i feel there's more value in keeping it but what is the hope for the property to do for us like is there a certain budget offset specifically we're going for and i'm just asking because i only see short-term returns on selling the property when if we keep and maintain it we could actually do something with it and the public could know that we could be pushed into doing something with it yeah thank you for the question i would say at this point uh we're looking at this with maximum flexibility i don't think that there is a definitive amount of money that we're looking to return on the property it really is this balance between what price is offered and
community benefit. One of the things that I think is a real benefit of using a real estate broker is hopefully we're going to reach a wider market and we're going to get a better sense of what is the highest and best use of the property. I think our first attempt or two at this, it was very
limited and this will give us a lot more information. At the end of the day, we also want
to make sure whatever is chosen is consistent with underlying land use, other objectives in
comp plan too but i don't think we'll know how to compare that until we get uh concrete offers on the table thank you we have one more yeah i guess i'll add in um do the proceeds from the sale go to the general fund and does the city have anything to pay down on the property uh like any this the funds will go to the general fund because that the property is owned by the the city of Lancaster not a utility or it's an asset of the city and there are no there's no outstanding debt related to this building as you recall we consolidated our fire stations and upgraded those facilities and so it is
our objective at least it's mine objective not to borrow more money to
address the considerable upgrades that are necessary in that facility thank you are there any further questions from the public hearing none I'll make a motion to move resolution 78 to full council on the 11th second all those in favor aye thank you so much the last item on our agenda before we close community planning this evening is administration bill number 14 amending the zoning ordinance for self storage facilities good evening ladies I have a short presentation that I wanted to provide to the council members as well as to the mayor regarding this text amendment and I think Renard has it he can share it thank you and then I'll discuss mainly the text amendment portion but this is for both the text amendment and a zoning map amendment and Claudia shank who's the applicant applicants representative will provide more information on the map
amendment so before you tonight is a text a zoning text amendment to allow for self storage facilities larger than 20,000 square feet by right in the central manufacturing or CM zoning district and a zoning map amendment to
rezone a 2.5 5 to acre parcel from c3 regional commercial zoning to CM Currently self-storage facilities are allowed in our zoning ordinance only up to 20,000 square feet in area. They are allowed by right in the CM district and they are allowed by special exception in the R3, R4 mixed-use and CM district. The
ordinance currently does not provide for any self-storage facilities exceeding 20,000 square feet in any district which has resulted in zoning variances being
approved to allow larger facilities without having specific standards being in place as you may be aware self-storage facilities have changed significantly over time in the past rows of old garages were converted into self-storage facilities the current trend though is to create large scaled structures or adaptively reused structures that are climate controlled features with mostly interior access for storage so this proposed amendment will address that market change the amendment would allow for self self self-storage facilities without size restrictions on lots um that are a minimum of three acres and a maximum of five acres they do not have access to a public street and they have been in existence since july 1st 2025. these were requirements um minor the two starred ones were requirements that were requested by the city planning commission to be added to the application or to the text amendment one of the things that
that we're featuring with the new storage self-storage with this text
amendment is to require new design requirements for the CM district so design standards for buildings would be required for any building over 50,000 square feet in gross floor area these these are attempt to provide sorry Bernard can you change to the next one sorry it should be the new design required there you go thank you so the things that we're looking at were building entrances that are distinguishable breaking up facades so that they're not blank walls for a specific distance providing flat roofs with parapet so it's not just a flat roof but it has some architectural structure to it and then that all rooftop equipment is screened from you and that would be section 300-20 that would be a new section to the zoning ordinance and again that's for all CM districts for buildings over 50,000 square feet the other requirement requirements that would be new would be specific requirements for self storage they must be climate controlled buildings they have to have a minimum height of two feet or two stories buffering and screening would be required for exterior garage type doors facing public right-of-way security fencing would be required and outdoor storage of vehicles must be located in the side or rear yard and the surface must be paved I would note that we are if you sorry Bernard if you could change
to the next thank you self storage facilities that are less than 20,000 square feet in area would be removed from a special exception use. This would
allow would not allow any self-storage in R3 and R4 and that's just some of the some other remnants from the previous zoning ordinance that are the current zoning ordinance that have just kind of had an impact on some of the like having self-storage in more of these residential areas. So we requested they'd be removed so that would create potentially two non-conforming uses based on our on our research and then just a quick brief review of the process that we've gone through so far between January and June if the next slide please the Planning Bureau has worked with the applicant reviewing draft amendments and provided recommended changes in September the City Planning commission recommended minor changes to the zoning amendment with those changes they recommended approval of the draft ordinance and map amendment for city council the county planning commission will review the zoning amendment for consistency with places 20 40 on november 8th and then we are requesting to have a first reading at city council on november 11th and a second reading in public hearing on november 25th i will turn it over to claudia good evening i'm claudia shank I'm an attorney with McNeese Wallace and Nurek and I represent oak tree development group and its affiliate
1031 Dillerville Road LP which is the owner of the property that was the catalyst for this application So oak tree has done a number of projects in the city over the past several years Including the city gate project that you may be familiar with A few others I'd point out the RGS building at 53 West James Street
UPMC outpatient center which included a green roof and 512 North Market Street which is a combination of office and residential use just to familiarize yourself with yourselves with the group here that's proposing the development
what you're looking at on the screen or as exhibit one in your packet is is again the property that's the catalyst for this application it's a roughly two and a half acre unit within a two unit condo association it's located primarily in the c3 regional commercial district with a small portion being in the cm central manufacturing zoning
district it's currently improved with commercial buildings one of which is leased to an automotive repair shop and several other outbuildings oak tree doesn't feel that it's the highest and best use of the property and wants to redevelop it at the same time there are a number of site constraints that make redevelopment of this property challenging most notably it doesn't have any public street access so it gains access to the from dillerville road over an
easement that is on the lands to the south the shopping center and so we want to develop the property commercially we feel it's appropriate for commercial use but it's not appropriate for
anything that would be a high trip generator in terms of traffic because of that configuration so as betsy mentioned we have been we've been working on this amendment since before betsy joined the staff here since she's been on board we've been working
very closely with her to try to bring this to council and again i think betsy did a good job of summarizing the amendment what we're proposing to do on this site would be a self-storage facility of approximately 120 000 square feet most of the units would be accessed from the interior of the building so a little bit different from the traditional drive up self-storage facility
that you may be familiar with again your ordinance currently doesn't allow anything over 20 000
square feet and you know what we've seen that has done is sort of encourage some of the smaller type facilities garages and some of the residential areas being permitted for that those storage uses if you could go to the next slide bernie so this is just an excerpt from the zoning map and shows
the property that we're talking about this evening and the zoning to the north being in the cm zoning district that we would propose to extend to the south and incorporate our property which is
currently in in the c3 or the pink betsy did provide a full list of all the criteria that would an applicant would be required to meet in order to construct a self-storage facility without size restriction another thing i just want to point out to the council that there is another building on this property between the shopping center and the buildings that we're discussing elliott's garage that was recently sold to heck construction that's one of the units within the
two unit site condo they're going to be converting that building for an office use and so we're looking forward to that being part of the overall redevelopment of this site if you could go to the
next sheet bernie all right so i wanted to give council a sense of the impact of the amendment across the city so this is currently a map showing where self-storage facilities are permitted to
day so green areas they're permitted by special exception orange areas they're permitted by right of course there is that maximum limitation of 20,000 square feet and if you go to the next slide you can see the impact that this amendment
would have so here you're seeing dark blue are places where they would be permitted by right up to 20,000 square feet light blue would be permitted by special exception up to 20,000 square feet and orange would be permitted above 20,000 square feet which is really just our property we originally had proposed a version of this that was a little broader and would have applied to a few
additional sites but Planning Commission really wanted to see that narrowed down certainly it could be expanded in the future if if council saw fit or if there was another site where it was appropriate I think Betsy did a great job walking through the design standards I do want to emphasize that those would apply not just to self storage facilities but to all buildings over
50,000 square feet in the CM district. So with that background, I will have Mr. Smornick come forward briefly. He is the project engineer with David Miller Associates, and I'll let him walk you through the site plan and some renderings of the project. Next slide, please.
Good evening. Yes, referring to the plan, I am Bill Smornick with David Miller Associates. If you look at the plan, there is a proposal that large square building is roughly 200 feet on a
side. That would be the storage facility. As Claudia has outlined, the access to the site is from on this exhibit would be to the left. There is a crosshatch access easement that you can see
highlighted in yellow. That would be the point at which vehicles would access the site. Once they were on the property, there would be a parking opportunity in the front of the building with the main entrance into the office space on the front side towards dillardville road and then working around the building there would be a gate that would be a secure area to the right to the north
of the on the property and then continue around to the north side and then to the east side and then another gate so there'd be full vehicular movement around the building i think if you go
to the slide with the rendering it would be helpful this is the existing conditions okay there's the proposed building you can see the heck
construction improvement on the building that is to the south and then this is
the vision the architecture architectural concept for the building again parking along the Dillardville Road property frontage and then that gate and then enclosed area again to the north and around to the rear of the building the site is served by public sewer mortar and it would be reconstructed to allow for access for connection to the proposed structure storm water management would be accomplished one of the primary elements would be the elimination of impervious areas on the site to reduce the amount of impervious on the site and additionally we need to establish the management facility for runoff, the two inch storm for the site. Parking would be some access, the parking criteria generally would be those visiting to establish an arrangement, rental arrangement for the space. There really is no other need for other parking employee parking is minimal there would be some exterior
storage of vehicles again on the side and rear of the building all right and could you bernie just flip back to the previous page briefly right so this is a google map image of the property now
so i just want to emphasize the significant cleanup and change that would occur you can flip back to the next slide as a part of this redevelopment we're estimating that it would be approximately conservatively an additional 200 000 in annual tax revenue that would be generated through this redevelopment so i want to emphasize that as well from a planning perspective we believe it's consistent with the comprehensive plan which identifies this area as being used for general commercial or industrial purposes and also focuses on underutilized properties and the redevelopment of those i know that self-storage is not always a use that everyone
gets excited about but our research really indicates that this area is underserved in that regard and we think by putting it on a property where it's appropriate and taking it out of some of the residential areas where it perhaps is not we're achieving a good balance
in terms of redeveloping this site and supporting the city's overall planning objective so i will note for council that also with me this evening is eric scott from oak tree nate jones with storage construction who is the project designer and builder and alyssa quinn
with asset management who would provide the on-site management services and alyssa has a lot of the data around need and the market research that that led us to this use a lot of time and thought was put into how this property should be used in order to
arrive at this is the solution so we're happy to answer any questions that
that council has thank you um talk to me a little bit about um the entrance it just
the site plan if you go to the concept plan i don't know if i have a pointer or access to a pointer but um um nope too far you had it you had it okay so if you see the cross hatched area that's highlighted in yellow yes goes up to the frontage kind of across from where the road wise yes that is the primary entrance to the site that is afforded to this use there is a parking lot surrounding the commercial shopping center to the south south being on the left-hand side of this drawing but primarily access to the site is attained through that cross hatched area until you get on to the property where heck is gonna relocate and that's the bluish green colored portion of the lot and then on the pinkish colored rose colored property uh parking area that that would be the property for the self-storage facility so you would gain access at that location and then move to the north along paralleling dillardville road the reason there is not direct access off of this property if you have been through this area it's a
significant grade change it's uh the approach to go over the railroad track so there's a about a i would say probably close to a 15 or 18 foot grade change right at the front of the property
so that you can't get direct access off of dillardville road thank you um so what do you believe the impact will be for like some of the other businesses in and around that particular location while you're doing construction to get this up to where it needs to be
what what would be the impact yes um there would be a temporary impact with the moving in of
equipment to allow for the construction demolition of the existing uses and then for the construction i think following the actual establishment of the business there would be a reduction in the amount of trips and vehicle trips because it's a fairly low chip generator for the self-storage
probably consolidated onto you know an individual day of the week versus being a lot more traffic
going over there but during construction access would have to come through that corridor and there would be the movement of equipment materials both removal of the buildings and bringing in
new building construction materials okay so has the the businesses that are that currently exist along that little strip there have have they been spoken to as anybody had conversation with them can you please come up to the mic or any mic anyone that's working well I'm Eric Scott without tree so that currently the improved property consists of Elliott's garage and two Quonset huts starting with the Quonset hut the smaller Quonset hut is just used for an oak tree affiliated entity for storage the other is an outside entity just used for storage so that entity and Elliott's garage has a lease that's expiring at the end of February so we've had Elliott as a tenant for a long time I don't want to represent his side of the discussion but his time is coming to an end anyhow regardless of lease agreement okay so and both cuz you know I answered part a
which is the uses that currently exist on the parcel that we're proposing to
redevelop so if that's on the right so if you go right to left heck construction does a lot of our construction for other projects he's personally excited about this project okay and i don't view much disruption at all to the retail tenants to the left we have not had that conversation yet but typically we cordon off
the construction site with temporary fencing and really monitor the entry and exit of those
vehicles so i don't know that the retail people will be affected that much but we'll certainly have the conversation this project moves forward thank you um are there any questions from count from the committee thank you councillor craig um i'd probably be the first to admit that um storage units don't really excite me i think when looking at this project i'm curious about the size of the footprint increasing it beyond 20 000 would that if we did not approve that amendment to the zoning ordinance would that stop the project from moving forward yes we would sell
the property okay and going back i kind of want to hang out on the question around the small
businesses that are uh currently on the footprint how many total businesses are currently on the footprint there's really one primary business the two quonset huts are used for storage to simplify
that discussion there's one current business elliot's auto garage and and you're saying that their lease is ending and there will be their lease is ending and there's other issues where
elliot's not going to have much use for the property after that timetable anyhow okay and as far as I know that you had mentioned there was research done on productive uses for this property were there other options that were considered for the development of this area that would fit the current zoning we can we've
considered every option I've been with oak tree for almost 11 years now we've considered every possible option I just not on I think one other consideration
is the the ability to have a high turnover retail space is really challenging because you're going to be drawing traffic across those uh other uses which is an impact to their use and this use it provides for there's a lot of space to put a building there
but if you were to occupy that let's say at a ratio that a retail space or some other
higher employee count business would be it would be really a challenge to get the folks in and out of there plus the service vehicles to get in would be really challenging as well can i underscore that point i find myself going on dillerville road quite frequently and have occasion to go
in to that shopping plaza because i like ethiopian food it is very difficult to navigate out of that parking lot so much so that the church that occupies on sundays has somebody out front
directing traffic because there's a merge that's coming off of harrisburg pike and three lanes of traffic on dillerville road and so i appreciate that the use that's being considered for this is a low trip use even though i also appreciate council arroyo that a um you know highest best
use you know not i'm not you know storage facility got it you know i have and for this particular
site also sitting down off of the it's just the visibility is also really difficult um because it's not at grade with dillerville road itself so those are just that's just my two cents the only thing i was going to tag on to that is it's not just trip generation and high volume it's also The one we considered most seriously was an industrial building but to get trucks in and out of that building is extremely
Problematic so it's the industrial side that's difficult any other use that requires
More visits than a few visits a day was problematic as well
Are there any further questions from the committee? I mean from council as a whole Council Craig, thank you So I guess Betsy this question might be for you I want to kind of Kind of connect the dots like how we got from this project and we talked about
You know the challenges in the site and I frequent that shopping center as well and it's challenging But how did we get from there to the zoning amendments because I see that The how do we arrive at the removal of the special exception
Understanding that it's a limited. It's more limited and more on the map
but it is also removing the special exception so can you talk about how we got to that sure removing the r3 and r4 special exceptions was something that
we've received a couple of requests to the zoning hearing board over the last well since I've started basically related to self storage and the expansion of self storage they might like there might be existing facilities that are you know 10,000 square feet and they want to expand and the we don't have any specific requirements for self-storage and how that's to be developed so a lot of the existing facilities are you know old carriage
houses that have been converted but those seem to be going away I think one
example is the one tonight with the historic Commission those are like five units that are going to be removed for housing but when we were looking at it I've just had a concern since I've started that there's no release no real standards for self storage and that well I mean they have parking requirements and other zoning standards new development that's being proposed is being approved without for example the zoning hearing board approved additional A new facility that was twice the size of what's permitted several months ago in the CM district But we wouldn't have the kind of standards that we're proposing with this text amendment. I see where that trade-off is happening Thank you for that counselor colleagues Thank You constable. Thank you for the presentation. Are there any local partners or neighborhood organizations? Involving the execution of this project yeah local partners and neighborhood organizations like are you talking about the design and construction team or construction yeah nate jones is here from storage construction
and nate can speak speak and introduce himself but they're out of york alissa is here from storage asset management she actually lives in lancaster her business is operated out of york
Pennsylvania and the design team is that it's as local as we could put together a design construction management team for that this type of specialty and and trades when we go to construction they'll be you know it still has to be bit out with all the trade contractors but I imagine there's going to be a very strong local presence in the construction this building thank you thank you going to agree any further questions from council as all council
Thank You councillor Craig um first just a comment I think what is being proposed
on the whole makes sense I definitely appreciate the like trade-off of you
know I think it's probably for the in the city's best interest to limit self storage out of residential and I mean I guess that's just my opinion but I also had a question which I just want to make sure I understand correctly so there's a clause in the table of uses that says something to the effect of like I'm just reading it here just do not have access to a public street and are in existence as of July 1st 2025 am I to understand that provision of the July 1st 2025 to mean that this is kind of the way of saying well if a parcel were to be redrawn or rezoned just kind of you know preventing a situation where maybe we look at the use map now and we're good with where we feel these storage facilities are allowed but we don't necessarily want a situation where again
if a parcels to be redrawn or if it's to be rezoned you know suddenly we're like
oh there's a self storage you know somebody could build a huge self storage
facility there and we don't you know our zoning doesn't match that is that kind
of the intention that's exactly right but we're primarily thinking about would be a lot consolidation because that's something that anyone could do by right
they could consolidate multiple CM lots to meet the requirements so this would prevent that from happening a rezoning could still occur but that would have to
come before council in order to take place fair enough thank you okay any
further questions from council as well I'll entertain questions or comments from the public 700 block new holland avenue i just wanted to comment from more of a contextual standpoint
uh when this did come to planning commission i do share your anxiety about storage units
i do think we're getting a good trade-off by preventing these in our currently zoned residential areas i also was concerned about expanding the permission of storage units in
our community but that's why the commission had conversation to really narrow this down to one site to prevent it from being a prolific thing and also the um as mr hirsch is pointing out with the date being affixed to it this is a good example of a property that suffers under our current
ordinances and why we really need to light the fire to redo our zoning ordinances in general
i personally felt a little bit of feelings for the circumstance because it was kind of expressed that
that this was a holding pattern until more clarity could be provided by a zoning update, which they hadn't gotten, which is why they came to us with this amendment.
So yeah, it's not perfect as far as what we might wanna see with the comp plan, but I think this is the most practical, from my standpoint, the most practical solution
we could get under the current context to protect the community, but also advance the community forward. that's just what i wanted to say for the record and everyone have a good night thank you are there any further questions from the public comments thank you so much um i'll make a motion to move
bill number 14 2025 to full council on the 11th for first reading second all those in favor aye Thank you so much Council president that concludes community planning. Thank you very much councillor Craig get reconnected here And we will now move to the Public Works Committee councillor Hirsch
Thank You council president The Public Works Committee has one agenda item on it one item on its agenda this evening, which is resolution 75
authorizing
another
Local shares account program application, but since this one is directly from the public works Department it's coming through public works and the director of public works director Campbell's here. Let's talk about it
Thank you very much. Thank you very much for this opportunity as As council member her should mentioned
It's very similar to and follow follows the same guidelines as the LSA that all the LSA's that have been described under Cped This particular request is for authorizing an application to local shares for street safety and stormwater management improvements for East Ross between North Queen Street and North Chippen Street. The overall project cost we anticipate to be approximately $1.5 million, where $325,000 of that would be for design and engineering costs and construction would be about 1.2 million dollars. The design would take place during the year of 2026 and the construction hopefully would
take place during 27 and 28 so that it would be done before planned surface paving scheduled
for 2029 and 2030. is an this is an interesting opportunity in different question different kind of a question because if we don't have access to this kind of funding which is grant funding we may not be able to do this particular type of stormwater management this is part of this it's a combination of safe streets for all and vision zero plus stormwater management at every opportunity that we have to look at streetscape development we also look at the opportunities for stormwater management as you all know we have very limited access to funding sources for stormwater work and this actually from from north queen to shippen has the potential of managing up to four acres of surface stormwater runoff and in fact depending on how creative our engineers are it could manage up to
six acres of of runoff by comparison the the uh the storm water management uh that has been installed up at mccaskey manages about nine acres it's not it doesn't manage the entire site but
what has already been installed manages about nine acres so that is significant there's also on different stretches of of Ross Street some localized flooding in that area that needs to be addressed so at this moment we've could we continue to seek grant funding for implementation while the design proceeds we've already
received 35,000 from the Chesapeake Bay Trust from their g3 or green towns green
streets green jobs program for the for design which puts us in a much better position to be able to make up and to go after grant funding to make up any other shortfall
if we don't get the full million that is being requested for this against this 1.5 million dollar project i'm very open to questions at this moment thank you director campbell um so i read this with great interest i happen to live along this the stretch of street that we're talking
about so it's exciting hopefully we get the grant I have a couple just two questions I don't know
from what I read that it's explicitly stated but I'm assuming we're talking about like rain gardens
or would there be other potential types of infrastructure with this it's a very good
question we would primarily be looking at rain gardens and other kinds of for Bay or other green infrastructure installations however because of the potential to be able to manage a significant amount of water that we it may allow for smaller
retention tanks as well this is not technically part of the McCaskey basin however part of it is part of the North Basin which goes to the stormwater management on the north end of the city and part of it is also under the the what we what we call
the southern basin which is every the water that goes to to edge uh edge comb not edge comb angle side angle side thank you for some reason i have some something else it's been a long day But so it does address two particular storm sheds that we're looking at managing in detail Thank you. And then my second question. I just wanted to clarify around the cost
I think I heard you said that the design and engineering is going to be approximately
325,000 and then construction at 1.2 So I might have conclude that the rough cost of the project is going to be One point five ish million. That is correct. We don't anticipate that it would be anything larger than that It's difficult to sustain that much more or much more than that Unless suddenly in the investigation we find that there are extraordinary new opportunities for storage management But otherwise, we're we're looking at streetscape development for bays rain gardens things like that Thank you. That makes sense bit to a tree to the tree canopy as well that's good to know um thank you director campbell
i will open it up to questions from the public works committee or full council
and i'll also offer are there any comments uh or questions from the public um darlene bird ann street i know we borrowed a lot of money for stormwater and for sewer we just had another pen vest grant how much of the city is not covered in the money that we're borrowing that we're looking to take a million dollars to just do raw street are there other areas in the city that will not be included in all the money that we borrow to do water and stormwater management so i do think that's a good question but this the advantage of this is that it's a grant so if we do not have access to this it really is the case that we may not be able to take advantage of this opportunity and provide stormwater management at this particular location we just do not have other funds does not include the whole city there are areas that are excluded from the plan that we presented I was here last year that we presented when we got bonds for all this that we went into debt for it didn't include doing stormwater management for the city just certain areas. If I could venture to answer your question I think
what I'm hearing Director Campbell saying is that for one this particular project would not go forward without the grant like without the grant it's not going to happen is kind of what I'm picking up.
The stormwater part would not.
We would still be able to go forward with some of the vision 0 implementation but we would then have a sealed new installation and we would not reopen
that for stormwater management at a future date. DIRECTOR DEWOLF Okay. I was just going to add that I would recommend
consulting the capital plan because I think it lays out nicely like where the funds are coming
from when they're going to be spent when the projects are going to be done.
I think that's just to answer your question.
I think that's probably the best guide as far as where those borrowings that you're talking about are going and that kind of thing. right because i know we asked these questions when they were talking about borrowing the money and getting a bond and how much they were getting a bond for and it was explained to us about the storm water management and that it was for the city not certain parts of the city so i think it would include ross street and i do think that the trees and the other areas you're talking about could be covered under other grant monies that we got like division zero where we decided to put daylight poles all around maybe rain gardens would have been something better to use that money for if we could or other things for that particular block or i guess it's a couple blocks i think i do understand and appreciate some of the questions that you're asking um different types of infrastructure are funded in different ways um what we have asked for in the capital plan does not solve all stormwater issues throughout the entire city it is trying to be as not selective but trying to be as focused as practical what is the low the low-hanging fruit that we can actually address as well as major challenges that do need to be addressed one way or the other but it was the request for the in the past would not solve all stormwater issues we look at every streetscape implementation as an opportunity to see if we can address stormwater in a different way and here's a particular stretch of of roadway that was not initially anticipated as stormwater management but has a great potential to manage up to four to six acres of of surface drainage so i think that's we're looking at it as an opportunity recognizing that if if it is not Funded as such we would still go forward with it with the vision zero aspects, but would not be able to do stormwater management Council Hirsch. Yeah, dr. Campbell
So I want to kind of paraphrase and try to venture an answer to that as well When stormwater is concerned you have to build projects where the stormwater Yes tends to lie. Okay. Thank you. Thank you Opportunities to build the infrastructure that's necessary to manage it. Got it. Thank you. Are there any other comments from the public hearing none I will make a motion to move resolution 75 to our full meeting of Council on November 11th say again all those in favor aye thank you and that concludes the Public Works Committee Thank You councillor Hirsch counselors that will take us to our committee of the whole we have three items on our agenda this evening the first is administration resolution number 73 that is authorizing a flag raising flag raising at City Hall
to mark Dominican Independence Day the dates that they have proposed are
February 24th 2026 with a backup date of the 27th in case of inclement weather
and this application was submitted by the Dominican Association of Lancaster and meets our at least 120 day in advance threshold counselors any
comments on the resolution from the public hearing none we'll make a motion to move resolution number 73 2025 to our next meeting of council on the 11th second motion and a second all in favor aye any opposed okay thank you we also
have administration resolution number 76 approving a management agreement with the Central Market Trust dr. Campbell I thought you might be back for this one
welcome back my pleasure thank you very much as well this this request is to approve a management agreement between the city of Lancaster and Central Market Trust and enter into an agreement with Central Market Trust which had been
treat Central Market Trust which had been created in 2005 with a management
agreement which was established in 2006 and then was amended in 2015 it needs new agreement to update to actual practices best management practices at the request of CMT but also mutually wanted by the city by us in the city one of its key purposes or several of its key purposes are to develop clear definitions of terminology such as what constitutes budget
capital improvement fund capital improvement plan capital improvement projects and capital items among other terminology it would eliminate
burdensome requirements that CMT retained 50% of its annual net profits with 50% going into maintenance reserve fund and therefore give them the
liberty to to utilize those funds in ways that they see fit requires the establishment of annual budgets, which is consistent with not only our practices, but consistent with the needs as established by the Home Rule Charter, although it's not related to the Home Rule Charter.
It implements a new procedure for capital improvement planning and projects, including confirmation that work is consistent with the facility condition assessments that have
been performed for that facility as well. It does require that $10,000 annually be contributed from the CMT to the Capital Improvement Fund for capital projects as identified in that annual capital planning process,
and it would establish new and clarified sections regarding repairs and maintenance.
Many of those definitions have been not only unclear but had been inconsistently managed in the past.
what why would we be doing this it redresses some problematic disclarities related to the existing contract it will align the BMPs or the best management practices of property management it responds to the needs identified by both
parties and it clarifies what is and is what and what is not capital eligible that too had been a major area of discomfort it it had taken the full basically a full rewrite over the course of the past several months almost the better part of a year for this for this rewrite with the consent and input of both sets of parties it becomes significantly more straightforward in
terms of its key responsibilities the construction versus maintenance clarity of purpose and the clarity most importantly of the owner which is the city versus the manager which is the cmt responsibilities thank you director campbell um i'm excited that this is coming before us i know that it's very long overdue and i'm also excited to hear that the central market trust um is is in agreement and alignment with these um these practices i think there has been a lot of ambiguity in the past having previously served on the board and so I appreciate the updates that are here and if you
could just you mentioned a capital improvement plan and it's mentioned in
in the agreement can you speak a little bit about the frequency that that's updated who updates that and who agrees on what's on that list that's that's an integral part of what's in this agreement so the capital plan would be
would be reviewed on an annual basis so that it would be looking first and
foremost at what the facility condition assessment already indicates as needed for the building and the responsibilities of the city are maintaining the envelope of the building and primary systems such as the electrical and the HVAC but not specific to any particular vendor so it's the overall HVAC for the facility the overall structure of the facility etc and the facility condition assessment which we will be updating on a periodic basis will be the basis for that however the plan will be proposed by the operator by CMT and we would be presented to the city saying these are the things that we believe are necessary to be done either to have to provide for their their the stand holders or to provide for other improvements as they see fit and that would be a discussion between both parties on an annual basis we would review what can be paid for what we what the CMT and the fund foundation can afford as well as what is the key responsibility of the city versus the responsibility of the of the CMT and those decisions would be made jointly and that would be the basis of the capital plan for that year thank
you councillors any additional comments or questions
council Hirsch Thank You council president my question is just a lot of what's been said makes sense I am curious though about the input from the Central Market Trust my understanding is that they currently still do not have an executive director although someone can correct me if I'm wrong who from the Central Market Trust like I assume the board of directors were the ones that would have given input into this amendment and I guess over what time was that done and I guess I'm just like curious about the input from their perspective leading up to this resolution we see now they have partnered
with us all the way through I think I can also just say that this that we had gone through several iterations over an extended period of time I think like 18 months yeah I think it's been a bit longer than that because it started when I was actually on the Central Market Board as the representative from the
city and so it's been a quite an iterative process and there's been a lot
of people involved from the board and executive directors both passed and well
they don't have one currently but staff as well and I would just say that the that their legal counsel was the final review and that is what got us to here and so it has been a long journey that's helpful thank you thank you counselor men Thank You council president and thank you director Campbell's my only question is is it a function of the board with the representative from the city to make sure this is executed to the liking of both parties or is the
city gonna have to do due diligence to make sure that the capital plan is happening and the expenditures are what they're supposed to be is this gonna be just like a board joint effort or is this gonna be extra work in time for city staff to go back and audit expenditures so the building is still owned by the city and so it is our responsibility to make sure that it remains in good working order functionally structurally and that it can operate for its intended use and the board of CMT has a vested interest in making sure that it is operating to its best intention
as well. So I think there's a push me pull you on both sides mutual mutual engagement to make it happen if one party falls short the other the other party does have in this agreement
means of holding the others accountable and i would just add the agreement is actually i mean we we feel like it's actually going to be more efficient for both parties as well so thank you and that concludes my questions thank you any additional comments from council from the public all right thank you both hearing none I would make a motion to move resolution
number 76 2025 to our next meeting on the 11th I have a motion a second all in favor aye any opposed thank you and lastly on our committee of the whole
agenda this evening we have council bill number 15 2025 this is being introduced by council Craig Thank You council president it's addressing the an increase in salary for council members it has been two decades almost two
decades was January 25th 2000 no December 20 no December 5th I believe December 5th 2005 and I think they voted on it in 2006 to make it almost two decades so next year would be two decades since council has had a salary
increase so not only would it not affect anybody sitting on the dais at the moment unless it would be I think counselor med if or maybe hers if they ran again but the current people sitting here unless they run again it would not affect any of us and would not would start on would be effective January the 8th I mean January of 2028 so and I I wanted to address this and I think this
is probably the perfect time to do so because it's it is time for elections
and it wasn't wouldn't be used as an election tool because it's effective date is so far out and council members are required to not only attend and participate and do the work for council but also are required to be on other
boards throughout the city and that's pretty much all I have to say about it
because there's you know the the facts are there and that's it thank you very
much counselor Craig I um I'll share counselor oh go ahead just one other thing in comparison
and I did a little research income I I looked up um York and Harrisburg Harris actually Harrisburg's population is lower than Lancaster's I find that amazing but um I looked up Harrisburg um Scranton Altoona different cities around Pennsylvania that have the close to the same
population maybe a little under a little over just to kind of gauge where their council salaries are
some of their council salaries are incredible um Harrisburg right off the top of my head I don't remember the exact figure but I think Harrisburg might be somewhere around 20 and you know they're probably although Harrisburg is the capital their population is less than Lancaster Pennsylvania and all right that's just a little amazing that's it Thank You council Craig I knew that this is something that you've been thinking about as you know your service on council is winding down and I appreciate you know where you're coming from with
with this proposal I don't think that anybody serves on council in this
part-time capacity part-time in quotation marks capacity for the salary but I do think it's not insignificant to note that it's been very long time that there's been any sort of change and also not insignificant to note that nobody sitting on this dais without being reelected would have any benefit from
the passage of this bill I think that that's super important and also not for nothing the Home Rule Charter does mandate an increased number of meetings and and increased involvement in budgeting processes and I think that that the time should be recognized but also the level of accountability for
voters should also be recognized so if council members aren't coming to those meetings or meeting their commitments or being an active participant in those
things all the more incentive voters have to pay attention to those things so I just want to thank councillor Craig for bringing this forward I think the timing is yeah it's never perfect timing but I think that the timing with you
know the end of the year coming the election being tomorrow is is about as as you're going to get so that's pretty much it thank you um other comments from members of council councillor ahmed thank you council president and thank you councillor craig for bringing this
forward i think that it has been a long time and i think this will also allow other folks in the community who may have not been interested in running for council to look into running for council if they gave additional means for them to do so i would also like to add you know that i am
up for reelection and if I were to be elected tomorrow I do plan on abstaining from the vote given that it would affect the last year of my second term and that
concludes my comments Thank You councillor men I'd want to double check
that but it might I guess because the timing of the election so okay thank you
additional comments from council if I may council president councillor yeah
yeah and forgive me if this was already explained councillor Craig but in your comments but the overall cost of council would actually be lower compared to pre
home rule era so the homo charter made it that city council members do not receive benefits from the city so even with this slight increase to the salary compensation overall council would be receiving less compensation as a package compared to the pre home rule era so that's also worth noting for the public thank you additional comments from council councilor that's present was it stated with the just for the record like what the increase is because I and if I
missed it let me know but it is the the resolution calls for a $2,000 across the board increase for each individual council person and the additional 500 for council president because of their because the council president duties
thank you cuz I just want to put in perspective I calculated using a CPI so
inflation calculator based on when the $8,000 salary was passed today that would be worth over 13 and a half thousand so you know y'all heard my
budget comments earlier and my concerns I think the fact that so I full disclosure I wasn't sure how I felt about this when I saw it on our agenda
but you know looking at that and saying okay it wouldn't even necessarily keep
up with inflation for what it was said at 2005 but I think it's nice that there an increase and i also feel better about it knowing that it's effective 2028 so i'm not voted on my own you know um on my current term so those things kind of made me feel a little better about it so thank you any additional comments from council comments from the public all right hearing
none i will hear a motion or i will make a motion to move council bill number 15 2025 to our agenda It's a bill so it'll be for a first reading at our meeting on November 11th motion to approve
Second motion and a second. I'm gonna do a voice vote on this one. Mr. Harris if you would when you're ready Yes, madam president. Mr. Mudd. Aye. Mr. Roya. Aye. Mr. Cleese. All right, miss Craig. All right, miss Diaz Mr. Hirsch. All right, President Baker. Aye Thank you very much counselors The last item on our agenda this evening is the clerk's report Confirming mr. Harris that you have submitted that in writing to us. I have thank you very much Then having reached the conclusion of our agenda. I'll hear a motion to adjourn Motion to adjourn second motion a second all in favor aye. We're adjourned. Thank you